In 1994, I walked into a prison in Cambodia,
عام 1994، ذهبت إلى سجن في كمبوديا،
and I met a 12-year-old boy
وقابلت صبي عمره 12 عاما
who had been tortured
تم تعذيبه
and was denied access to counsel.
وتم حرمانه من المحامي.
And as I looked into his eyes, I realized
وحينما نظرت لعينيه، أدركت
that for the hundreds of letters I had written
أنه ضمن مئات الخطابات التي كتبتها
for political prisoners, that I would never have
من أجل السجناء السياسيين، لم أكتب
written a letter for him,
خطابا لأجله
because he was not a 12-year-old boy who
لأن عمره 12 عاما ولم يكن
had done something important for anybody.
قد فعل شيئا مهماً لأي شخص
He was not a political prisoner.
فهو لم يكن سجيناً سياسيا
He was a 12-year-old boy who had
لقد كان صبي قام
stolen a bicycle.
بسرقة دراجة
What I also realized at that point was that
وما أدركته أيضاً في تلك اللحظة
it was not only Cambodia, but
لم يكن فقط في كمبوديا، لكن
of the 113
في 113 دولة نامية
developing countries that torture,
يستخدمون التعذيب
93 of these countries have all passed laws
منهم 93 دولة قامت بالمصادقة على قوانين
that say you have a right to a lawyer
أن لديك حق الحصول على محامي
and you have a right not to be tortured.
وأن لديك الحق بعدم تعذيبك
And what I recognized was that there was an
وما أدركته أيضاً كان
incredible window of opportunity for us
نافذة مذهلة من الفرص بالنسبة لنا
as a world community to come together
كمجتمع دولي لنجتمع سويا
and end torture as an investigative tool.
وننهي التعذيب كوسيلة للتحقيق مع المتهم
We often think of torture as being
نحن عادةً ما نعتبر التعذيب
political torture or reserved for
من الناحية السياسية أو يحصل
just the worst, but, in fact,
للأشخاص السيئين فقط، لكن
95 percent of torture today
95% من التعذيب اليوم
is not for political prisoners.
ليس للسجناء السياسيين
It is for people who are
إنه للناس الذين
in broken-down legal systems,
قاموا بخرق القانون
and unfortunately because torture is
وبكل أسف لأن التعذيب
the cheapest form of investigation --
هو أرخص أنواع التحقيق كلفة --
it's cheaper than having a legal system,
إنه أرخص من الحصول على نظام قانوني،
cheaper than having a lawyer
وأرخص من تعيين محامي
and early access to counsel --
وحصول مبكر على مستشار --
it is what happens most of the time.
وهو ما يحدث في أغلب الأوقات.
I believe today that it is possible for us
أعتقد أن بامكاننا اليوم
as a world community, if we make a decision,
كمجتمع دولي، إذا اخذنا قرارا،
to come together and end torture
لنجتمع سويا وننهي التعذيب
as an investigative tool in our lifetime,
كوسيلة للتحقيق خلال فترة حياتنا
but it will require three things.
لكننا سنحتاج لثلاثة أشياء.
First is the training, empowerment,
أولاً هو تدريب، و تمكين،
and connection of defenders worldwide.
وتشبيك مكافحي التعذيب في العالم.
The second is insuring that there is
والثاني هو التأكد من
systematic early access to counsel.
الحصول المبكر للإستشارة بصورة منهجية
And the third is commitment.
والثالث هو الإلتزام.
So in the year 2000,
لذا في عام 2000
I began to wonder,
بدأت أستعجب
what if we came together?
ماذا لو أجتمعنا سوياً؟
Could we do something
هل يمكننا فعل شئ
for these 93 countries?
لهذه الـ 93 دولة؟
And I founded International Bridges to Justice
فقمت بتسأسيس الجسر العالمي للعدالة
which has a specific mission of
التي لديها مهمة محددة
ending torture as an investigative tool
لإنهاء التعذيب كوسيلة للتحقيق
and implementing due process rights
وتنفيذ الإجراءات القانونية الواجبة
in the 93 countries by placing trained lawyers
في الـ 93 دولة بتعيين محامين مدربين
at an early stage in police stations
وفي مرحلة مبكرة في مخافر الشرطة
and in courtrooms.
وقاعات المحاكم.
My first experiences, though, did come
وقد كانت أولى تجاربي من
from Cambodia, and at the time I remember
دولة كمبوديا، وأذكر في المرة الأولى
first coming to Cambodia and there were,
التي وصلت فيها كمبوديا
in 1994, still less than
عام 1994، كان يوجد أقل
10 attorneys in the country because
من 10 محامين في البلاد لأن
the Khmer Rouge had killed them all.
الخمير الحمر قاموا بقتلهم جميعاً.
And even 20 years later, there was only
وحتى بعد 20 عاما
10 lawyers in the country, so consequently
ظلوا 10 محامين في البلاد، لذا عادة
you'd walk into a prison and
تذهب الى السجن و
not only would you meet 12-year-old boys,
ليس فقط تجد صبي عمره 12 عاما
you'd meet women and you'd say,
بل تجد إمرأة وحينما تسألها
"Why are you here?" Women would say,
"لماذا أنت هنا؟" تجيب المرأة
"Well I've been here for 10 years because
" أنا هنا منذ 10 سنوات لأن
my husband committed a crime, but they can't find him."
زوجي أرتكب جريمة، ولم يعثروا عليه."
So it's just a place where there was no rule of law.
لذا فهو مكان بلا سيادة للقانون
The first group of defenders came together
أول مجموعة للمكافحين إجتمعوا سويا
and I still remember, as I was training, I said,
ومازلت أذكر، بينما كنت أدربهم، قلت
"Okay, what do you do for an investigation?"
" حسناً، ماذا تفعلوا خلال التحقيقات؟"
And there was silence in the class, and finally
وساد الصمت في الغرفة، وأخيراً
one woman stood up, [inaudible name],
فقامت إمرأة،
and she said "Khrew," which means "teacher."
وقالت " خروي، الذي يعني "معلمة."
She said, "I have defended more than
قالت، " لقد دافعت عن أكثر من
a hundred people, and I've never had to do
مائة شخص، ولم يحصل أن قمت
any investigation,
بأي تحقيقات،
because they all come with confessions."
لأن جميعهم قاموا بالإعتراف."
And we talked about, as a class, the fact that
وقد تحدثنا عن ذلك في الفصل، و
number one, the confessions
أن السبب الأول، الإعترافات
might not be reliable, but number two,
ربما لا تكون حقيقية، لكننا
we did not want to encourage the police
لم نرغب في حث الشرطة
to keep doing this, especially
على مواصلة ذلك، خصوصاً
as it was now against the law.
لأنه أصبح مخالفاً للقانون الآن.
And it took a lot of courage for these
وقد تطلب الكثير من الشجاعة
defenders to decide that they would
لأولئك المكافحين حيث
begin to stand up and support each other
بدأوا في التكتل ودعم بعضهم البعض
in implementing these laws.
في تنفيذ القوانين.
And I still remember the first cases where
ومازلت أذكر أولى القضايا حيث
they came, all 25 together, she would
جاءوا جميعاً 25 محامي، تقف
stand up, and they were in the back, and
إحداهن و يقوم البقية في الخلف
they would support her, and the judges kept
بدعمها، ويبدأ القاضي في القول
saying, "No, no, no, no, we're going to do things
" لا ، لا ، لا، سنقوم بفعل هذه الأشياء
the exact same way we've been doing them."
بنفس الطريقة التي كنا نقوم بها سابقاً."
But one day the perfect case came, and it
حتى جاءت القضية المثالية، وقد
was a woman who was a vegetable seller,
كانت إمرأة تبيع الخضار،
she was sitting outside of a house.
وكانت تجلس خارج منزلها
She said she actually saw the person
وقالت أنها رأت الشخص
run out who she thinks stole
الذي يجري وتعتقد أنه سرق
whatever the jewelry was, but the police
شيئ من المجوهرات، لكن الشرطة
came, they got her, there was nothing on her.
جاءت وأخذوها، ولم تكن مدانة
She was pregnant at the time. She had
وقد كانت حامل في ذلك الوقت. وعليها
cigarette burns on her. She'd miscarried.
حروق سجائر. وقد أجهضت
And when they brought her case
وحينما جاءوا بقضيتها
to the judge, for the first time he stood up
للقاضي، لأول مرة وقف
and he said, "Yes, there's no evidence
وقال، " نعم، لا توجد بينة
except for your torture confession
باستثناء الإعتراف بالتعذيب
and you will be released."
وسيتم إطلاق سراحك."
And the defenders began to take cases
وبدأ المكافحون بأخذ القضايا
over and over again and
واحدة تلو الأخرى و
you will see, they have step by step began
تلاحظ خطوة بخطوة بدأوا
to change the course of history in Cambodia.
بتغيير التاريخ في كمبوديا
But Cambodia is not alone.
لكن كمبوديا ليست وحدها
I used to think, well is it Cambodia?
كنت أفكر، هل الأمر قاصر على كمبوديا؟
Or is it other countries?
أم أنه في بلدان أخرى
But it is in so many countries.
لكنه في كثير من البلدان
In Burundi I walked into a prison and it wasn't
في بورندي ذهبت الى السجن ولم يكن
a 12-year-old boy, it was an 8-year-old boy
الأمر حول صبي عمره 12 عاماً، بل 8 أعوام
for stealing a mobile phone.
لسرقته هاتفاً محمولاً
Or a woman, I picked up her baby,
وإمرأة حملت طفلها،
really cute baby, I said "Your baby is so cute."
طفل جميل جداً، وقلت لها " طفلك جميل جداً."
It wasn't a baby, she was three.
لم يكن طفلة ، كان عمرها 3 أعوام
And she said "Yeah, but she's why I'm here,"
فقالت " نعم، هي سبب وجودي هنا"
because she was accused of stealing
لأنها أُتهمت بسرقة
two diapers and an iron for her baby and
حفاضين ومكواة لطفلتها و
still had been in prison.
هي ماتزال قابعة في السجن
And when I walked up to the prison director,
وعندما ذهبت لمدير السجن
I said, "You've got to let her out.
وقلت " ينبغي أن تتركها تذهب.
A judge would let her out."
سيخرجها القاضي."
And he said, "Okay, we can talk about it,
قال لي، " حسناً، يمكننا الحديث حول الأمر
but look at my prison. Eighty percent
لكن أنظري الى السجن. 80%
of the two thousand people here
من الألفين نزيل هنا
are without a lawyer. What can we do?"
ليس لديهم محامي، ماذا نفعل؟"
So lawyers began to courageously
لذا بدأ المحامون بكل شجاعة
stand up together to organize a system
بالوقوف سوياً وترتيب نظام
where they can take cases.
يستطيعون أخذ القضايا عبره
But we realized that it's not only the training
لكننا أدركنا أن ذلك ليس مجرد تدريب
of the lawyers, but the connection
للمحامين، بل يتعدى للتشبيك
of the lawyers that makes a difference.
والتواصل بين المحامين لإحداث فرق
For example, in Cambodia, it was that
كمثال، في كمبوديا، لم يكن الأمر
[inaudible name] did not go alone
أنها لم تذهب بمفردها
but she had 24 lawyers with her
لكن كان بصحبتها 24 محامي
who stood up together. And in the same way,
وقفوا سوياً. وبنفس الطريقة
in China, they always tell me,
في الصين، يخبروني دائماً
"It's like a fresh wind in the desert
" الأمر مثل الرياح العاتية في الصحراء
when we can come together."
حينما نكون سوياً."
Or in Zimbabwe, where I remember Innocent,
أو في زيمبابوي، حيث أذكر حادثة
after coming out of a prison where everybody
عقب الخروج من سجن وقف فيه الجميع
stood up and said, "I've been here
وقالوا، " نحن هنا منذ
for one year, eight years, 12 years
سنة، 8 سنوات، 12 سنة
without a lawyer,"
بدون محامي،"
he came and we had a training together
لقد جاءوا وتدربنا سوياً
and he said, "I have heard it said" --
وقال ، " لقد سمعت القول" --
because he had heard people mumbling
لأنه سمع الناس يهمهمون
and grumbling -- "I have heard it said that
ويتمتمون-- " لقد سمعت القول بأننا
we cannot help to create justice
لا يمكن أن نحقق العدالة
because we do not have the resources."
لأننا لا نملك الموارد."
And then he said, "But I want you to know
ثم قال، " لكني أريدك أن تعرفي
that the lack of resources
بأن قصور الموارد
is never an excuse for injustice."
ليس عذراً للظلم."
And with that, he successfully
ولذلك، نجح في
organized 68 lawyers who have been
تنظيم 68 محامي كانوا
systematically taking the cases.
يأخذون القضايا بصورة مستديمة
The key that we see, though, is training
المفتاح هو التدريب
and then early access.
ثم الوصول المبكر
I was recently in Egypt, and was inspired
وقد كنت مؤخراً في مصر، وقد ألهمني
to meet with another group of lawyers,
لقاء مجموعة أخرى من المحامين
and what they told me is that they said,
وقد أخبروني بأنهم قالوا،
"Hey, look, we don't have police
" أنظروا، ليس لدينا شرطة
on the streets now. The police are
في الطرقات الآن. الشرطة هي
one of the main reasons why we had
أحد الأسباب الرئيسية لقيامنا
the revolution. They were torturing everybody
بالثورة. كانوا يعذبون الجميع
all the time."
طوال الوقت."
And I said, "But there's been tens of millions
وقد قلت، " لكن كان هناك عشرات الملايين
of dollars that have recently gone in
من الدولارات ذهبت مؤخراً
to the development of the legal system here.
لتطوير النظام القانوني هنا.
What's going on?"
ماذا يحدث"
I met with one of the development agencies,
لقد إلتقيت مع أحدى وكالات التنمية،
and they were training prosecutors
وقد كانوا مدربين نيابة
and judges, which is the normal bias,
وقضاة، وهو الإنحياز المعتاد،
as opposed to defenders.
مقابل مكافحي التعذيب.
And they showed me a manual which
وقد عرضوا عليّ كتيبا
actually was an excellent manual.
كان كتيباً ممتازاً.
I said, "I'm gonna copy this."
فقلت، " سآخذ نسخة من هذا."
It had everything in it. Lawyers can come
كان فيه كل شئ. يمكن للمحامين القدوم
at the police station. It was perfect.
لمخفر الشرطة. كان ممتازاً.
Prosecutors were perfectly trained.
كان وكلاء النيابة مدربين بصورة ممتازة.
But I said to them, "I just have one question,
لكن قلت لهم، "لديّ سؤال واحد فقط،
which is, by the time that everybody got to
وهو، بحلول الوقت الذي يصل الجميع
the prosecutor's office, what had happened to them?"
فيه لمكتب النيابة، ماذا حدث لهم؟"
And after a pause, they said,
وبعد صمت، قالوا،
"They had been tortured."
"يكون قد تم تعذيبهم."
So the pieces are,
إذاً فالنقاط هي،
not only the training of the lawyers, but
ليس مجرد محامين مدربين، لكن
us finding a way to systematically implement
أن نجد طريقة لتطبيق الوصول
early access to counsel, because they are
المبكر بصورة منهجية إلى الإستشارة، لأنهم
the safeguard in the system
صمام الأمان في النظام
for people who are being tortured.
لأؤلئك الذين يتم تعذيبهم.
And as I tell you this, I'm also aware of the
وبينما أحدثكم عن هذا، أنا أدرك حقيقة
fact that it sounds like, "Oh, okay, it sounds
أن ذلك يبدو مثل ، " أوه، حسناً،
like we could do it, but can we really do it?"
ظاهر الأمر أننا أستطعنا فعلها، لكن هل نستطيع بالفعل؟"
Because it sounds big.
لأن الأمر يبدو ضخماً
And there are many reasons why I believe it's possible.
وهناك الكثير من الأسباب التي أعتقد أنها ممكنة
The first reason is the people on the ground
السبب الأول هو الناس على الأرض
who find ways of creating miracles
الذين يجدون طرقاً لصنع المعجزات
because of their commitment.
بسبب إلتزامهم
It's not only Innocent, who I told you about
ليس فقط للأبرياء، الذين أخبرتكم عنهم
in Zimbabwe, but defenders all over the world
في زيمبابوي، لكن المكافحين في كل العالم
who are looking for these pieces.
الذين يتابعون هذه النقاط؟
We have a program called JusticeMakers,
لدينا برنامج يسمى صانعوا العدالة،
and we realized there are people that are
وقد أدركنا أن الناس
courageous and want to do things, but
شجعان ويريدون تطبيق العدالة، لكن
how can we support them?
كيف يمكننا دعمهم؟
So it's an online contest where it's only
لذا فهي مسابقة على الإنترنت حيث
five thousand dollars if you come up with
تحصل على 5 ألف دولار اذا اقترحت
and innovative way of implementing justice.
طريقة مبتكرة لتطبيق العدالة
And there are 30 JusticeMakers
وهناك 30 صانع عدالة
throughout the world, from Sri Lanka
عبر العالم، من سيرلانكا
to Swaziland to the DRC, who with
إلى شوازيلاند، الى الكونغو، الذين
five thousand dollars do amazing things,
يفعلون أشياء رائعة ب 5 آلاف دولار
through SMS programs,
عبر برامج الرسائل النصية
through paralegal programs,
وعبر شبه البرامج
through whatever they can do.
وعبر كل ما يستطيعون فعله
And it's not only these JusticeMakers,
وليس فقط عبر صانعوا العدالة
but people we courageously see
لكن أيضاً الناس الذين نشهد بشجاعة
figure out who their networks are
ونتعرف على شبكاتهم
and how they can move it forward.
وكيف يمكنهم المضي قدماً
So in China, for instance, great laws
لذا في الصين، قوانين عظيمة
came out where it says police cannot
جاءت لتنص على عدم تعذيب
torture people or they will be punished.
الشرطة للناس أو يتعرض الشرطي للعقاب
And I was sitting side by side with one of our
وكنت أجلس بجانب أحد
very courageous lawyers, and said,
صانعوا العدالة الشجعان، وقال،
"How can we get this out? How can we
" كيف يمكننا نشر هذا للجميع؟ كيف يمكننا
make sure that this is implemented?
التأكد من سلامة التطبيق؟
This is fantastic." And he said to me,
هذا رائع." وقال لي،
"Well, do you have money?" And I said,
"حسناً، هل لديك المال؟" فقلت،
"No." And he said, "That's okay,
" لا"، فقال، " حسناً لا بأس،
we can still figure it out."
يمكننا تدبر الأمر"
And on December 4, he organized
وفي الرابع من ديسمبر، قام بتنظيم
three thousand members
ثلاثة آلالاف عضو
of the Youth Communist League,
لرابطة الشباب الشيوعي
from 14 of the top law schools,
من 14 من أرفع كليات القانون،
who organized themselves, developed
الذين أنتظموا، وقاموا بتطوير
posters with the new laws, and went
ملصقات بالقوانين الجديدة، وذهبوا
to the police stations and began what he says
لمخافر الشرطة وبدأوا ما يسميه
is a non-violent legal revolution
بالثورة القانونية السلمية
to protect citizen rights.
لحماية حقوق المواطنين.
So I talked about the fact that we need
إذاً فقد تحدثت عن حقيقة حوجتنا
to train and support defenders.
لتدريب ودعم المكافحين.
We need to systematically implement
نحتاج لتطبيق منهجي
early access to counsel.
لوصول مبكر للمستشار القانوني
But the third and most important thing is that
لكن الشئ الثالث الأكثر أهمية هو
we make a commitment to this.
الإلتزام بهذا
And people often say to me, "You know,
وعادة ما يقول الناس، " تعرفون،
this is great, but it's wildly idealistic.
هذا عظيم ولكن مثالي جداً.
Never going to happen."
لن يحدث مطلقاً."
And the reason that I think that
والسبب الذي أعتقد
those words are interesting is because
أن هذه الكلمات مثيرة هو لأنها
those were the same kinds of words
كانت نفس نوع الكلمات
that were used for people who decided
التي أستخدمها الناس الذين قرروا
they would end slavery, or end apartheid.
إنهاء العبودية، وإنهاء التفرقة العنصرية.
It began with a small group of people
لقد بدأت بمجموعة صغيرة
who decided they would commit.
قررت بأنها ستلتزم
Now, there's one of our favorite poems
الآن، هناك قصيدة محبوبة
from the defenders, which they share
للمكافحين، يتقاسمونها
from each other, is:
مع بعضهم البعض وهي:
"Take courage friends, the road is often long,
"كن شجاعاً يا صديقي، الدرب دائماً طويل،
the path is never clear,
والمسار ليس واضحاً قطعاً،
and the stakes are very high,
والأجزاء عالية جداً،
but deep down, you are not alone."
لكن في الأعماق، أنت لست بمفردك."
And I believe that if we can come together
وأعتقد أننا اذا اجتمعنا سويا
as a world community to support not only
كمجتمع دولي لدعم ليس فقط
defenders, but also everyone in the system
المكافحين، لكن الجميع في النظام
who is looking towards it,
الذين يتطلعون قدماً لذلك
we can end torture as an investigative tool.
فيمكننا إنهاء التعذيب كوسيلة للتحقيق
I end always, because I'm sure the questions are --
أنا دائماً أنهي، لأنني متأكدة من الأسئلة هناك--
and I'd be happy to talk to you
وسأكون سعيدة للحديث معكم
at any point -- "But what can I really do?"
في أي نقطة-- " لكن ماذا نستطيع أن نفعل حقاً؟"
Well, I would say this. First of all,
حسناً، سأقول، أولاً،
you know what you can do. But second of all,
تعرفون مالذي ستفعلون. ثانياً،
I would leave you with the story of Vishna,
سأترككم مع قصة فيشنا،
who actually was my inspiration
الذي كان ملهماً لي
for starting International Bridges to Justice.
لبدء الجسر العالمي للعدالة.
Vishna was a 4-year-old boy when I met him
فيشنا صبي عمره 4 سنوات حينما التقيته
who was born in a Cambodian prison
وُلد في سجن كمبودي
in Kandal Province. But because he was
في محافظة كاندال. لكن لأنه وُلد
born in the prison, everybody loved him,
في السجن، أحبه الجميع،
including the guards, so he was the only one
حتى الحراس، لذا فقد كان الوحيد
who was allowed to come
المسموح له بالمجئ
in and out of the bars.
والخروج من الزنزانة
So, you know, there's bars. And by the time
كما تعلمون هناك زانزن. وبمرور الوقت
that Vishna was getting bigger,
الذين كبر فيه فيشنا
which means what gets bigger? Your head gets bigger.
ما يعني أن كل شئ يكبر؟ عقلك يكبر
So he would come to the first bar,
لذا فهو يأتي للزنزانة الأولى
the second bar and then the third bar,
والثانية والزنزانة الثالثة،
and then really slowly move his head
ثم ببطء يدخل رأسه
so he could fit through, and come back,
بحيث يستقيم عبر الفتحة، ويرجع
third, second, first. And he would
الثالثة، الثانية، الأولى. ويلتقط
grab my pinkie, because what he wanted
الخنصر، لأنه اراد
to do every day is he wanted to go visit.
زيارة جميع السجناء بصورة يومية
You know, he never quite made it to
كما تعلمون لم يستطع فعل ذلك
all of them every day, but he wanted to visit
كل يوم، لكنه أراد زيارة
all 156 prisoners. And I would lift him,
جميع الـ 156 سجين. وأقوم برفعه
and he would put his fingers through.
ويضع أصابعه عبر الزنزانة
Or if they were dark cells, it was like iron
أو اذا كانت زنزانة مظلمة، فهي مثلك الحديد
corrugated, and he would put his fingers through.
المموج، ويضع هو أصابعه عبرها
And most of the prisoners said that he was
وقد قال معظم السجناء أنه كان
their greatest joy and their sunshine, and they
أكبر متعة لهم وشروق شمسهم، بحيث
looked forward to him. And I was like,
يبحثون عنه. وقد كنت هكذا
here's Vishna. He's a 4-year-old boy.
ها هو فيشنا. إنه صبي ذا 4 أعوام.
He was born in a prison with almost nothing,
لقد وُلد في السجن بدون أي شئ تقريباً
no material goods, but he had a sense of
بدون مستلزماته، لكن لديه حس
his own heroic journey, which I believe
برحلته البطولية، التي أعتقد
we are all born into. He said,
أننا جميعاً ولدنا خلالها. قال فيشنا،
"Probably I can't do everything.
" على الأرجح لا أستطيع فعل شئ
But I'm one. I can do something.
لكني واحد. أستطيع فعل شئ.
And I will do the one thing that I can do."
وسوف أفعل الشيء الوحيد الذي يمكنني القيام به ."
So I thank you for having the prophetic
لذا أشكركم على الخيال
imagination to imagine the shaping
الرسالي لتصور تشكيل
of a new world with us together,
عالم جديد لنا جميعاً،
and invite you into this journey with us.
وأدعوكم للذهاب في هذه الرحلة معنا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)